[Music]
just quickly going to read your little
thing I wrote about John today in an
op-ed for the daily blog CIA torture
whistleblower John Kiriakou was
recruited from the high school that he
taught jared leto at in the decades to
follow he traveled the world recruited
other spies in turn and oversaw
operations that captured al-qaeda
militants and sent them to Guantanamo
Bay
eventually ah trains to keep secrets
there was one he could not live with his
government was torturing people
eventually he shared what he knew with
his fellow countrymen but tonight he
will share it with New Zealand and the
world so John please anyway tell us your
story about all the messages that you
have to give thank you so much for
having me for doing this for giving me
the opportunity the soapbox I'm happy to
do it and I'll apologize for the
lighting it's a I have every light on in
my in my room and it's still a if you're
not light enough anyway um you're right
I was I was recruited into the CIA when
I was in graduate school I was teaching
high school at the time at a private
school in Washington DC and as it turned
out my graduate school adviser was a CIA
officer undercover as a graduate school
adviser and he was the one who recruited
me into the agency I had never really
considered the CIA but I was getting
ready to graduate and I didn't have a
job I was getting married soon after
graduation I really needed the work and
the idea of seeing the world was
exciting to me and so I said sure I'll
go through the process so I did I went
through the process
God hired started on the first of
January 1990 and started working as an
analyst so really I was sitting in a
cubicle
thinking the big thoughts writing
writing papers for the president the
vice-president the secretaries of state
and defense the National Security
Advisor
and that was great it was a lot of fun
for a while and then I got bored went
overseas also as an analyst to the
Middle East learned to speak Arabic and
then went back to headquarters again in
1997 again I was bored and so into not
not 2000 in 1998 I made a very unusual
switch from analysis to counterterrorism
operations and and went overseas as a as
an Operations Officer like actually
trying to infiltrate terrorist groups
and either disrupt future attacks or
break up the group and found that I had
a knack for it it was dangerous
certainly but it was interesting it was
fun it was important and so I decided
well maybe I found my my place my niche
I went back to CIA headquarters after
serving overseas in 2000 and
September 11th hit in 2001 that changed
everything at the CIA as it turned out
the CIA after 2001 returned to its roots
the CIA that I had come of age in was
not the real CIA the real CIA was one
that that requires great oversight and
one that that is constantly pushing the
bounds of morals and ethics and legality
but I was as angry as every other
American on September 11th and I
volunteered certainly a good Afghanistan
and fight or do whatever was necessary
what I ended up doing was I was sent to
Pakistan as the chief of CIA
counterterrorism operations there and it
was in that job that in early 2002 I led
a series of raids that resulted in the
capture of Abu Zubaydah whom the CIA
believed at the time was the number
three in al-qaeda and many dozens I'm
not allowed to say the exact number but
many dozens of al-qaeda fighters at and
safe houses all over Pakistan well I had
occasion after capturing up as a beta to
have a long conversation with him in
fact I am i sat with him for 54
consecutive hours after his capture he
was very upset as you could imagine he
cried a lot he said that he would never
know the touch of a woman he would never
know the joy of fatherhood and I said
listen you are not the victim here there
were 50,000 people in those towers what
did you think we were going to do did
you think we weren't going to try to
find you to capture you or to find her
or kill bin Laden and he said that he
never wanted to attack the United States
on September 11th he wanted to attack
Israel he said all he ever wanted to do
was to kill Jews and I said listen I am
the nicest guy that you're going to meet
in this experience
my colleagues are not as nice as I am so
if there's one thing that you do it's
that you should cooperate and he said
you seem like a nice man but you're the
enemy and I'll never cooperate
I said suit yourself later that night a
CI a private jet flew in three FBI
agents and I loaded him onto the plane
he asked me to hold his hand the whole
time and I wished him the best of luck
and I never saw him again well two
months later I returned to CIA
headquarters and on the strength of the
Abu Zubaydah capture I had been promoted
and I was named the executive assistant
to the CIA's deputy director for
operations and it was in that capacity
that I had access to literally
everything in the CIA every operation
every sensitive compartment everything
and it was in that position that I
realized that we had initiated this
torture program now I I was in the
cafeteria one day and a former colleague
from the CIA's Counterterrorism Center
approached me and said hey I'm glad I
ran into you
do you have any interest in being and
these were his words certified in the
use of enhanced interrogation techniques
I had never heard the term before so I
asked him what it meant and he said very
excitedly we're gonna start getting
rough with these guys and I said well
what does that mean
and then he delineated these ten torture
techniques and I said well that sounds
like a torture program I said I think I
have a moral problem with that and I
declined well as it turned out of the
fourteen people that they approached
asking if they wanted to be trained in
these torture techniques I was the only
one who said no that was a source of
great disappointment for me but I kept
my mouth shut
I left the CIA two years later and still
kept my mouth shut but then in late 2007
I couldn't live with the
administration's lies anymore it seemed
like every time I turned on the
television President Bush was denying
that there was a torture program and the
CIA's director at the time and and
directors after him George Tenet were
all denying that there was a torture
program and I knew that that was a lie I
knew that they were lying to the
American people and I believe in
transparency I believe that the American
people have a right to know what their
country is doing in their name and so I
decided in December of 2007 that I was
going to blow the whistle on this
program and I gave a nationally
televised interview to ABC News in which
I did exactly that I said three things
three things that have utterly changed
the course of the rest of my life I said
that the CIA was torturing its prisoners
I said that torture was official US
government policy it was not the result
of a rogue as President Bush had said
and I said that the torture program had
been personally approved by the
President himself
as you can imagine within 24 hours the
FBI began investigating me and this is
where the story in my view becomes very
sad it becomes unamerican the FBI
investigated me for a full year from
December 2007 to December 2008 and they
decided at the end of that investigation
that I had not committed a crime that
the interview was not a crime because
the information was not inherently
classified and so they closed the
investigation four weeks later Barack
Obama was inaugurated as president of
the United States Barack Obama the
self-described most transparent
president in history and I should
preface this by saying that I believed
in the whole hope
change slogan of the Obama campaign not
just that I worked on the Obama campaign
I took my children to the inauguration
so they could see this historic moment
when when for the first time in history
an african-american man had become
president I mean this was an incredible
moment for America but what I did not
know was that as soon as he became
president the CIA asked Barack Obama to
secretly reopen the case against me
which he did I had no idea that I was
under investigation I had no idea that
the FBI was intercepting my phone calls
and was reading my emails and had teams
of surveillance on me and so I went
about my regular business so what was my
regular business well believe it or not
John Kerry who at the time was the
chairman of the Senate Foreign Relations
Committee called me and invited me to
join the Senate Foreign Relations
Committee staff as the chief
investigator investigating waste fraud
abuse and illegality in the State
Department and so I took that job again
having no idea that I was under FBI
investigation for what became five
felony charges the FBI investigated me
for three more years and finally in
January of 2012 I was charged with these
five felonies including three counts of
espionage espionage is one of the
gravest crimes with which an American
can be charged and frequently it carries
with it the death penalty
for telling the American people that the
CIA was torturing its prisoners now
there's something that happened in the
interim and I had no idea the
significance of it until this whole
thing was over one of the great things
the most wonderful things about working
for the Senate Foreign Relations
Committee is that you get to have lunch
with foreign diplomats all the time and
you know you get together for lunch you
talk about the events of the day
whatever happens to be in the paper you
talk about diplomacy I got a call one
day a totally normal and routine call
from a Japanese diplomat it was the
number three in the Japanese Embassy in
Washington and he invited me to lunch so
we went to a small restaurant on Capitol
Hill and I remember the lunch as being
delightful
I remember we talked about Israeli
elections and Turkish elections and the
arab-israeli peace process and at the
end of the lunch he said to me so what's
next for you and I said well I'm
actually thinking of resigning from the
Senate Foreign Relations Committee I
promised senator Kerry that I would give
him two years it's been two and a half
and I think I'd like to go into business
for myself I have five kids I need to
start saving some money for college I
think I'd like to go into the private
sector and very excitedly he said no
don't do that if you give me information
I can give you money and I said what's
wrong with you do you have any idea how
many times I've made that pitch in my
career shame on you I told him I ended
the lunch and I went directly to the
office of the Senate security officer
and I said I was just pitched by a
foreign intelligence officer and he said
oh is it that damn Russian again and I
said no no it's it's a Japanese of all
things and he said really a Japanese
okay he said well sometimes they like to
see what we're doing
visa vie trade and then he asked me to
write it up as a memo he was going to
send it to the FBI I said fine so I sat
there in his office and I wrote up the
memo he sent it to the FBI and then
called me the next day and said two FBI
agents were going to come and interview
me so they finally came up came to my
office and said okay here's what we want
you to do we want you to call him back
and we want you to try to get him to
tell you exactly what information he
wants and how much money he's willing to
pay for it I said okay do you want me to
wear a wire or something and they said
no we're gonna be at the next table and
we'll just listen to the conversation I
said fine so the morning of that lunch
they called me and said that something
had come up I should just go forward
with the lunch and write them another
memo so I met with this guy a second
time and then they asked me to meet with
him a third time and a fourth time and a
fifth time which I did because I'm a
patriot well I wrote up these memos
after each lunch and finally in the
fifth lunch he said that he had been
promoted he had been transferred to his
dream job and he was going to be the
number two in the Japanese embassy in
Cairo a year after that last lunch I was
arrested and we received discovery from
the Justice Department now discovery is
when the prosecution has to turn over to
the defense literally everything that
it's collected so that the defense can
use that to defend itself in this
discovery we found a series of memos the
first indicated that there never was any
Japanese diplomat he was an FBI agent
undercover
and he was trying to get me to commit
real espionage and I asked my lead
attorney why would they do such a thing
and he said because they have a
case and they know it's a case I
hadn't committed espionage I had blown
the whistle fair and square I told the
American people what they had a right to
know well we also received three memos
between the CIA and the Justice
Department the CIA wrote to the Justice
Department and said charged him with
espionage the Justice Department wrote
back and said but he hasn't committed
espionage and the CIA wrote back and
said charge him anyway and make him
defend himself and that was the Obama
administration now the Espionage Act
here in the United States was written in
1917 to combat German saboteurs during
the first world war between 1917 and
2009 it was used to charge three
Americans with espionage for talking to
the press just under the Obama
administration eight Americans were
charged with espionage for speaking to
the press the Obama administration used
the Espionage Act as an iron fist to
stamp out dissent
now I was a guy who always colored
within the lines I was nobody special
either there was nothing unusual about
me in any way I'm just a guy I'm just a
normal guy but one of the things that so
grossly disappointed me was that I was
the only one who said something you know
there were hundreds of people inside the
CIA who knew about this torture program
hundreds we now know from the Senate
torture report that people inside were
objecting to it they were writing cables
back from the secret prison saying this
is awful this is disgusting
a couple of them curtailed their
assignments which means they asked to
return to headquarters
it's a career-ending move but not a
single one of them said something
publicly even worse than that not a
single one of them ever said anything to
the Senate or House Intelligence
Committee the oversight committees I was
the only one who did that was a source
of great disappointment for me well in
the end Kim and I were talking about
this off camera a few minutes ago
and I had to defend myself against these
five felony charges I was facing 45
years in prison and over the course of
ten months our negotiations had brought
the Justice Department down to ten years
they wanted me to do ten years in a
federal penitentiary this was what they
called their best and final offer
and I turned it down and I said two
things I said first of all I haven't
done anything wrong
and because I haven't done anything
wrong I'm not doing ten minutes let
alone ten years in prison secondly I'm a
very longtime former CIA officer and in
my 15 years in the CIA
I witnessed hideous crimes against
humanity war crimes and I'm going to
have to testify in my own defense and I
might accidentally say something about
these horrible crimes that I've
witnessed my colleagues perpetrate over
the years and it might slip out in the
course of my my testimony
and so the CIA came back and said all
right dude
two and a half years you'll end up
serving under two I actually turned that
down and then one of my eleven attorneys
the one who I liked and respected the
most pulled me aside and said you just
don't get it
this isn't about innocence or guilt this
is about cutting your losses this is
about inflicting the least amount of
pain on yourself and your family it
doesn't matter whether you did it or
didn't do it the federal government wins
ninety eight point two percent of its
cases according to ProPublica and he
said if you were my brother I would beg
you to take this deal so I'm begging you
take the deal he said this can be a blip
in your life or it can be the defining
event of your life you can be home early
enough that your children won't even
remember you were gone or you can get
out when your children are in college
and so I took the deal it becomes an
economic decision with that said I would
do the whole damn thing over again
somebody had to say something
transparency is real it's important a
democracy can't function without
transparency and again the American
people have a right to know what their
government is doing in their name and so
I'm glad that I said something I'm glad
that I said something I'm glad that I
have continued to say something it's
cost me my marriage my wife left three
months ago she said it's just too much
work to be mrs. John Kiriakou to tell
you the truth I don't blame her
but I had to do the right thing and this
was the price that that we all have to
pay it was all worth it
thanks for listening
you